בוקר טוב, Boker tov, שנה טובה, Shana Tova, גמר חתימה טובה. Gmar
Chatima Tova. Today's דף Daf is the דף Daf we're sort of
up to today. We skipped today for יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, ט"ז.
Tet-Zayin. We pick up on ט"ו עמוד ב', Tet-Vav Amud Bet, the
two dots about a third of the way down. So we've definitely
got some ground to make up. We've been dealing with the debate
of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel if somebody sells a field and
it turns out that it was stolen, whether the person, the purchaser
can come back and get not only reimbursed for the principal, which
is obvious because it was a מקח טעות, Mekach ta'ut, but can
he also get reimbursed for the שבח Shevach for any improvements he
made. Is there presumed to be some insurance for that? And also
שמואל Shmuel said even if he was explicit, the seller, he can't
get it because it looks like ריבית. Ribbit. Okay, הכיר בה, Hika
bar, now we're going to deal with a one case even further
than that. הכיר בה שאינה שלו, Hikir bah she'eina shelo, the purchaser
here, I'm selling my field to Michael again, our standard purchaser, our
standard ראובן ושמעון. Reuven and Shimon. And Michael knows that it's stolen.
He knows I stole it, but he figures, heck, why not buy
it? I'll be able to get a good deal, he's selling it
at a discount, I'll be able to get a good few years
of produce off of it and until the, you know, until the
original owner can get it back from me. So Michael knows exactly
what he's getting himself into. Not nice behavior right after יום כיפור,
Yom Kippur, Michael. הכיר בה שאינה שלו ולקח. Hikir bah she'eina shelo
velakach. אמר רב, Amar Rav, says
רב, Rav, מעות יש לו שבח אין לו. Ma'ot yesh lo, shevach
ein lo. All right, he can still get his money back. He
can't get any improvements he made. He did sort of know what
he was getting
into. ושמואל אמר אפילו מעות אין לו. Ushmuel amar afilu ma'ot ein
lo. No, you can't get your money back. Now what's this debate
about? במאי קמיפלגי? Bemai kamiflagi? So what's this debate about? רב סבר,
Rav savar, אדם יודע שקרקע אין לו. Adam yode'a shekarka ein lo.
He knew that I didn't have the field. So then how do
we interpret why he was paying me for it knowing it wasn't
mine? So he knew it wasn't a real transaction. וגמר ונתן לשום
פיקדון. Vegamar venatan leshum pikadon.
So he gave me the money, we'll interpret it that he gave
me the money to hold on for him. It was just a
way of watching his money. Okay, which is strange.
So he knew he couldn't get the field for free, anyway?
Yeah, I mean it's very strange. Why would I give it to
you if I'd gone to all the trouble to steal it? Why
would I give it to you for free, right? So, you know,
the גמרא's Gemara going to interpret this as like a real question
of what do we think your intention was and so on. But
you know, the more obvious way of expressing it is like, how
would we legally choose to interpret this transaction, right? You knew it
wasn't. Presumably you were buying it because you knew you would be
able to get some years of use out of it, right, before
somebody came and took it back. So I didn't have a right
to sell it. So on the one hand, you know, but you
were paying me because you knew that was a way you could
get it. So what degree do we say no, legally it wasn't
a sale, you get your money back, or you were giving me
the money and I was giving it to you because of the
money, so therefore maybe you don't get your money back, right? So
we could have framed it as a legal question. It doesn't matter
what their intent was. Maybe we pretty much know their intent. But
if it wasn't a legal transaction, how do we then interpret it?
But the גמרא Gemara seems to make it about trying to get
into what somebody's intention is, which is a strange idea because right,
Michael, what, he's סתם Stam just giving me money to hold for
him? And like why would I give him the field if he
wasn't really giving me any money for me to keep? So let's
anyway go with the גמרא. Gemara. But that's the way the גמרא
Gemara takes
it. רב סבר, Rav savar, אדם יודע שקרקע אין לו. Adam yode'a
shekarka ein lo. You knew that I didn't have the field. וגמר
ונתן לשום פיקדון. Vegamar venatan leshum pikadon. So when you gave me
the money, it was just to watch for you. And therefore you
can ask for the money back. I mean, technically according to that,
you could ask for the money back a day later even before
the original owner comes. So it's really pretty much strange that that's
the real. And yeah, I know, that's what's so strange about this.
ונימא ליה לשום פיקדון. Venemaley leshum pikadon. So why not just tell
me, "Hey, Dov, will you hold on to this $1,000 for me?"
No, סבר לא מקבל. Savar lo mekabel. He figures look, Dov wouldn't
do that for me, it's a favor. You know, maybe it's like
in Europe where they've got negative interest rates. So anyway, he's not
going to hold on to the money for me. But if I
make it look like I'm buying the field from him, that's a
way to get him to hold on to the money for me.
All right. ושמואל סבר, Ushmuel savar,
that's רב's Rav position. ושמואל סבר, Ushmuel savar, אדם יודע שקרקע אין
לו. Adam yode'a shekarka ein lo.
Michael knew I didn't have the field. וגמר ונתן לשום מתנה. Vegamar
venatan leshum matana. He's giving me the money as a gift. Okay,
if he really just wants to gift me some money. ונימא ליה
לשום מתנה. Venemaley leshum matana. So say "Dov, I like you so
much, here's $1,000." No, כסיפא ליה מילתא. Ksef ley milsa. No, then
I'd be embarrassed to take it. So he figures this is a
way I can get Dov to take a gift from me without
embarrassing him by pretending to buy this field which I know isn't
his. Okay, now obviously that is so strange that either of those
is anybody's intent. But anyway, let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes
with this. ופליגי בחדא זימנא. Upoli b'chada zimna. Now,
don't they already debate a similar issue another different place? דאתמר, De'itmar,
was taught, המקדש את אחותו, Amekadesh et achoto,
somebody who marries his sister, gives his sister a nice gold ring
worth $100 and says הרי את מקודשת לי. Harei at mekudeshet li.
רב אמר מעות חוזרין. Rav amar ma'ot chozrin. All right, so she
has to give the money back. She has to give the ring
back. ושמואל אמר מעות מתנה. Ushmuel amar ma'ot matana. No, she gets
to keep the money. I mean, I'm saying money, whatever, she gets
to keep the money that was given as כסף קידושין. Kesef kidushin.
Same case where something clearly wasn't. doesn't binding, everybody knew it wasn't
binding. How do we interpret what that was that was given over?
Now obviously there's differences because in the case of the field, Michael
knows by giving me the money he's I'm going to let him,
you know, plow and use the field and whatever, and even though
we're all doing something illegal, but you know that's what he's going
to get me to let him go ahead and make use of
it. Right? You don't get anything out of this case with מקדש
אחותו, mekadesh achoto, so you know there it's a more reasonable type
of a debate.
But he really might be thinking that it really
is binding. Right, right, no, exactly.
Meaning even though he knows I don't legally own the field, he
might think that since I'm the de facto owner, maybe he does
have some way of getting some legal rights. Right? Whereas by מקדש
אחותו mekadesh achoto he's getting no benefit out of it, and there's
no sense that anything is binding. So there you could really ask,
what do we do with the money that was given over? Okay,
so anyway, but the גמרא Gemara thinks that the two cases are
very comparable. So the גמרא Gemara says so why do they have
to debate it in both cases? רבא אמר מעות חוזרין. Rava amar
maos chozrin. אדם יודע שאין קידושין תופסין
באחותו adam yodeia she-ein kiddushin tofsin be-achoto a person knows that he
can't marry his sister וגמר ונתן לשום פקדון ve-gamar ve-nasan leshum pikadon
so he just gives it to her to hold on to the
money for him. ונימא לה לשום פקדון? ve-neima lah leshum pikadon? So
just ask her to hold on to the money for him. No,
סברה לא מקבלה מיניה savra lo mekabela minei
she won't take it, but this way I'll get her to take
the money. ושמואל אמר מעות מתנה u-Shmuel amar maos matana
it's a gift ונתן לשום... ve-nasan leshum... I lost my place. מעות
מתנה. maos matana. אדם יודע שאין קידושין תופסין
באחותו adam yodeia she-ein kiddushin tofsin be-achoto a person knows that he
can't marry his sister וגמר ונתן לשום מתנה ve-gamar ve-nasan leshum matana
so what he's giving the money for as a gift. ונימא לה
לשום מתנה? ve-neima lah leshum matana? So tell her, here's a gift.
כיסופא דמילתא לא נסבה kisufa de-milsa lo nasva she'd be embarrassed to
accept a gift.
So why do you have to say it in both places since
we're giving the same explanation, even though as we said you could
give very different explanations? The גמרא Gemara says no, צריכא, tzricha, you
need both places. דאי איתמר בהא de-isamar be-ha if it was said
in the first case,
the case of the field בהא קאמר רבא דלא עביד איניש דשדי
מעותיו לנכרא be-ha ka'amar Rava de-lo avid inish de-shadi maosav le-nochra
people don't give gifts their money to some stranger, okay? So therefore
clearly there the money we'll look at as a type of a
פקדון. pikadon. אבל גבי אחותו aval gabi achoto by the sister אימא
מודה ליה לשמואל eima modeh lei le-Shmuel maybe he would agree to
Shmuel. It is his sister after all, so maybe I'd be more
inclined to interpret it as a gift. ואי איתמר בהא ve-isamar be-ha
and if it was said just about the case of the sister
בהא קאמר שמואל be-ha ka'amar Shmuel that's why Shmuel's prepared to say
it's a gift, because it's a sister. אבל בהא aval be-ha but
in the case of the field אימא מודה ליה לרבא eima modeh
lei le-Rava maybe he should agree to Rava that it's not a
gift, that it's a פקדון. pikadon. צריכא, tzricha, you need both cases.
Okay, so now the גמרא's Gemara explained that it's all a question
of getting into what his דעת da'as is. As we said, there
could obviously have been some different explanation in the case of the
field. So now the גמרא's Gemara going to push on that other
possibility. בין לרבא דאמר פקדון ובין לשמואל דאמר מתנה bein le-Rava de-amar
pikadon u-vein le-Shmuel de-amar matana whether for Rava says it's פקדון pikadon
and Shmuel says it's a gift האי לארעא במאי קא נחית ופירות
היכי אכיל? hai le-ara be-mai ka nachis u-peiros heichi achil?
He says why did, you know, Michael so, you know, why is
he basically... hold on let me just re-track for one second.
Right,
Michael clearly means to do more, this is exactly the question we
asked. Michael clearly means to do more than just give me a
gift or give me a פקדון, pikadon, because if all he was
doing was giving me a gift or a פקדון, pikadon, he'd give
me the money and walk away. But after he gives me the
money, what's he going to do? He's going to go move into
the field and start plowing it and planting it. So clearly the
nature of their transaction was not just as a gift or a
פקדון. pikadon. The nature of the transaction was that somehow by giving
me that money, as Michael said before, maybe he doesn't... רש"י Rashi
says maybe he doesn't know the הלכה, halacha, maybe he thinks he
actually is entitled to have rights in that field. So maybe that's
the debate where he knew it wasn't mine but thought that giving
me the money, he knew that in practice giving the money would
allow me, would make me let him use the field and maybe
even thought it got him legal rights, but legally speaking he doesn't
have rights. So what do we do in that case? Do I
get the money back... does he get the money back or not?
Okay, so maybe it's a more debate about, you know, having nothing
to do with his intent but about the legal realities of what's
going on. So the גמרא Gemara says, because or else why would
Michael start using the field? האי לארעא במאי קא נחית ופירות היכי
אכיל? hai le-ara be-mai ka nachis u-peiros heichi achil? If he was
just giving me a gift or פקדון, pikadon, on what basis is
he going into the field
and how is he eating the fruit? Clearly he thinks it's by
virtue of giving me the money and it's some type of a
transaction that's really going on here. So the גמרא Gemara says no,
סבר, savar, no, Michael figures, אנא איחות לארעא ואעביד ואכול כהיכי דהוי
קא עביד איהו ana eichus le-ara ve-avid ve-achul ke-heichi de-hava ka avid
ihu I'll go into the land and I'll work it and I'll
eat in it the same way that he would work in the
field, okay? לכי אתי מריה דארעא le-chi asi marei de-ara and when
and when the owner comes back, I'll give it back to the
owner. He says, 'I don't know, Dov is in the field, he's
planting it, he's benefiting from it, I'll do the same, not because
I think that my money I'm giving him forms any legal transaction,
but whatever the basis is that Dov is using Eli's field over
there, I'll also use Eli's field. When he comes and asks for
it back, I'll give it back to him.' Okay? And when the
owner comes back, לכי אתי מריה דארעא, le-chi asi marei de-ara, זוזי
ליהוו ליה לרבא דאמר פקדון פקדון zuzi le-havu lei le-Rava de-amar pikadon
pikadon then the money I gave Dov, when finally the field is
asked to go back, it'll either be according to Rava it'll be
a פקדון... pikadon... and he'll and Dov will give me the money
back or לשמואל דאמר מתנה מתנה l'Shmuel d'amar matanah matanah or שמואל
Shmuel says a gift, a gift. So meaning, although the גמרא Gemara
clearly recognizes that by giving me the money I'm letting him use
the field and we should sort of assess that the debate of
רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel is on that axis, like what does
it mean when he maybe believes he is giving him rights or
in practice he knows he needs to give him the money in
order to get rights, but technically it's not mine, how therefore what
should we be able to do with the money, the גמרא Gemara
like refuses to sort of see that that's really what's going on.
Says, no, you know, Michael is just going to use the field,
has nothing to do with the money he gave, you know, so
he figures the same way Dov was using the field, I'll use
the field or whatever, I'll give it back to the owner when
the owner shows up, and the question about מתנה matanah or פקדון
pikadon is he does not think is linked to his rights in
the field. That's just סתם stam a question. What do how we
treat it when somebody gives money in something that's not a legal
transaction. But you could understand that that's sort of exactly what the
גמרא Gemara is saying, that what the גמרא Gemara is really trying
to say is, is that we see this debate of רב Rav
and שמואל, Shmuel, that if somebody gave money under something that normally
would be a legal transaction and in this case it's not, what
do we do with the money? Do we let the other side
keep it or do we give it back? The fact that in
one particular case like a חוסו, choso, he knows he's getting nothing
out of it and in the other case like the field, he
actually in practice is getting something out of it and maybe even
thinks he's entitled to something, that doesn't change our determination. We're going
to make an across the board rule about what to do with
money when it's given in something that is not, you know, seems
to be a legal transaction but actually is not. Yes, do you
have a question? What? Isn't it a poor investment? Well, I'm presumably
selling it to him at a discount because I know that we
all know it's stolen. Anyway, but that's just his own choice whether
he wants, you know, how it's not a poor investment anyway if
he פוסק posken like רב, Rav, then he gets the money back.
Yeah, whatever. So you know, it's so improper, I'm sure he'll get
it at a discount. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay.
So that's that debate. Now we wrap up all of the discussions
we've had until now with רב Rav and שמואל, Shmuel, and although
we normally say that הלכה halacha is like שמואל Shmuel in דיני
dinei in דיני ממונות, dinei mamonot, שמואל Shmuel is going to be
the loser in all of these פסקים. psakim. So let's take a
look. הלכתא, hilcheta, the הלכה halacha is, says the גמרא, Gemara, אמר
רבא, amar Rava, הלכתא hilcheta is, the הלכה halacha is, יש לו
מעות ויש לו שבח. yesh lo maot v'yesh lo shevach. In the
first debate when he did not know that it was stolen but
it turned out to be stolen, can Michael come and get reimbursed
from me not only the principal which obviously he can כמקח טעות,
k'mekach taut, but also for his improvement or is there a concern
there that it looks like a type of a ריבית? ribit? And
not just expenses. Right, a whole שבח. shevach. So there we rule
like רב Rav that he is able to be reimbursed for the
שבח. shevach. Okay, יש לו מעות ויש לו שבח ואף על פי
שלא פירש. yesh lo maot v'yesh lo shevach v'af al pi shelo
perash. It's a full ruling like רב Rav even if I didn't
give him explicit insurance for the שבח, shevach, he's entitled to the
שבח. shevach. You remember שמואל Shmuel made the סופר sofer ask the
guy, do you want to insure the owner for the שבח? shevach?
Right, do you want to insure the owner in general, do you
want to insure him for the שבח? shevach? So here he's saying
like רב, Rav, he gets reimbursed for the principal and the שבח
shevach even if it wasn't written. Okay, there's a lot of protection
of the purchaser going on here. What? Is it considered מקח טעות?
mekach taut? Yeah, of course it's מקח טעות. mekach taut. Okay, הכיר
בה שאינה שלו, hekir bah she'eina shelo, the case we just did.
Michael knows it's not his, ולחקה, v'lakachah, and he purchases it. מעות
יש לו שבח אין לו. maot yesh lo shevach ein lo. Michael
even gets his money back. Okay, there's a lot of protecting of
the purchaser here. And not only that, אחריות טעות סופר הוא. achrayut
taut sofer hu. If the סופר sofer forgot to write, did not
write that there was a lean on the field, so that's considered
to just be an oversight, and any document has a lean in
it. בין בשטרי הלואה bein b'shitrei halva'ah by loan documents, which was
sort of, you know, what we were sort of I think presuming
or that was the חכמים chachamim of הברייתא, ha-beraita, but not only
that, בין בשטרי מקח
וממכר,
bein
b'shitrei mekach u-mimkar, right?
Again, I think this is against שמואל.
Shmuel. Even in a sale document where we said, you know, a
loan document, it's all about being reimbursed so you want to insure
the lean. A sale document, you hope you're never going to have
to get your money back. And we said maybe there there aren't
can't be presumed to be insurance. So we are saying no, any
type of thing, the purchaser is totally protected. Even if he knew
it wasn't his field, the guy's field, he gets his money back.
And in general, he buys a field and something happens, the original
owner takes it back, the creditor comes and seizes it, he is
able to go back to the seller even if nothing was written
in the document. It's presumed to be insured, and he gets back
his principal and he gets back his שבח. shevach. So the purchaser's
like totally protected, a consistent set of rulings against שמואל. Shmuel. Did
you have a question there, Jenna? Okay. So should it be the
entire value back or is it prorated? For instance, if if the
owner comes today versus 20 years from now, perhaps it might be
prorated because he used the benefit of using that field for 20
years. Yeah, you know, that's a good question, but since he owns
the field in perpetuity, there's no prorating. It's not like a lease,
right? It's like what do you get when you subtract 10 from
a thousand? You still have a thousand. I mean, not a thousand,
10 from infinity. You still have infinity. Right, so I I bought
that field for infinity. I mean, okay, you know, whatever. So so
then if it maybe it would make a
difference if there's a יובל, Yovel, but
if I bought the field for infinity even though I use it
for 10 years, the value is still the same. Okay, but it's
a good question, but I think it doesn't make, I'm pretty positive
it doesn't. You can't get the חזקה chazakah... *Chazakah*. Okay. So now
actually so that was a nice little wrap-up and a whole set
of פסקים *Pesakim* there to protect the purchaser against שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel*.
בעי מיניה שמואל מרב *Be'ei Minei Shmuel Mei-Rav*. Now שמואל *Shmuel* asks
רב Rav *Rav*. חזר ולקח מבעלים הראשונים מהו *Chazar Ve-Lakach Mi-Ba'alim Harishonim
Mahu*? Let's say that in this case that we just discussed, okay,
I sell it to Michael and Michael knows that it's stolen, okay,
and we're going to say that he'll get his, at least the
way we've now just finished פוסק pasken *paskening* like רב Rav. *Rav*
against שמואל *Shmuel*, he's going to get his money back, okay, but
anyway, now but let's even just bracket that right now. Michael knows
it's stolen. Now if אלי *Eli* the original owner comes, he
gets it back from Michael.
Let's say I go and I buy it from אלי *Eli*. You
got this? I stole it from אלי *Eli* and then I sold
it to Michael. Now with the money Michael just gave me or
something, I go and I buy it from אלי *Eli*, okay. Can
I now be like אלי *Eli* and go ahead and take the
field back from Michael? Hey Michael, that's my field you're on. It
was stolen before. I didn't have a right to sell you before.
Now it's really legitimately mine, give it back to me. Whether I
give you the money back or not depends on רב Rav *Rav*
and שמואל *Shmuel*. Or do we say no, my whole purpose of
buying it from אלי *Eli* was in order to make it a
legitimate sale what I did when I sold it to Michael. Now
there will be a question which we'll get to which is even
if that was my intention, what was the act of קנין *Kinyan*?
Right, if I sold it to him, right, on January 1 and
I buy it from אלי *Eli* on July 1, six months later,
it might be that I'm trying to now make that early sale
of six months ago legitimate, okay, but where was but it's only
now that I own it. So what now is that act of
קנין *Kinyan* of transaction that makes Michael, you know, own the field?
So we'll get to that later. But the first point is what's
my intent in buying it from אלי *Eli*? Is it basically now
I can seize it back from Michael or do we say no,
the whole point was was to legitimate the sale I did earlier.
Does it depend on what you do? Well, you would think like,
well, what am I saying? Am I saying here is my intent
or there is my intent? So again, this is a case where
we're just going to make a legal determination. You know, it's very
interesting. Not for one second do we think to ask the guy.
Let's say he stands up and he announces: I want it to
be known, I am buying it from אלי *Eli* for the purpose
of X. Will that make... it doesn't ever sound like that makes
a difference. But let's read the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Okay. So בעי
מיניה שמואל מרב חזר ולקח מבעלים הראשונים מהו *Be'ei Minei Shmuel Mei-Rav,
Chazar Ve-Lakach Mi-Ba'alim Harishonim Mahu*? What do we say? אמר ליה מה
מכר mecher. ראשון לשני *Amar Lei Mah Machar Rishon Le-Sheni*? I'm the
ראשון *Rishon*, Michael's the שני *Sheni*. What did I sell to Michael?
כל זכות שתבוא לידו *Kol Zechus She-Tavo Le-Yado*.
When I sold him the field and I didn't own the field
at the time, but essentially I was selling him any rights I
now have or in the future would have in the field, which
basically means that since in the end I buy the field, we
go back and we look at my original sale and we say
that makes
it Michael own it now because when I was selling it to
him I was basically telling him if I ever get any rights
in this field I'm going to give them over to you. Why
do we say that? So that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is
going to ask. מאי טעמא *Mai Ta'ama*? So here the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says, why do you say that? מר זוטרא אמר ניחא ליה
דלא ליקריוה גזלנא *Mar Zutra Amar Nichei Lei Delo Likreye Gazlana* because
I don't want, we assume that when I'm buying it from אלי
*Eli* there it's because I don't want אלי *Eli* to eventually take
it back from Michael and then Michael's going to call me a
גזלן gazlan, *Gazlan*. That's my תשובה *Teshuvah*. רב Rav, אשי אמר *Rav
Ashi Amar*, no, ניחא ליה דליקו בהימנותיה *Nichei Lei De-Leku Be-Heimanutei*. No,
I want, since I did the sale, I want to be seen
as a trustworthy person,
so I want the sale to be legitimate. Now that seems pretty
close. I want my, you know, my act to be seen as
valid and legitimate and to be shown that I'm trustworthy or I
don't want to be called a גזלן gazlan, *Gazlan*. Aren't they essentially
the same thing?
So that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to ask. מאי
בינייהו *Mai Beineihu*? What's the difference? דמית לוקח *De-Mis Loke'ach*. So the
לוקח *Loke'ach* died. So מאן דאמר ניחא ליה דלא ליקריוה גזלנא *Man
De-Amar Nichei Lei Delo Likreye Gazlana*, and then you know I buy
after the לוקח *Loke'ach* dies, I buy the field from אלי *Eli*,
okay? So if the owner dies... well we'll get... well okay, but
that's not a נפקא מינא *Nafke Minei* for this, okay? So if
the idea is that I don't want to get called a גזלן
gazlan, *Gazlan*, המית לוקח *Ha-Mis Loke'ach*, so the לוקח *Loke'ach* isn't going
to call me a גזלן gazlan. *Gazlan*, he's dead. Okay. If it's
about what the לוקח *Loke'ach* would... What about his kids? We'll get
to... well okay. ומאן דאמר ניחא ליה דליקו בהימנותיה *U-Man De-Amar Nichei
Lei De-Leku Be-Heimanutei*, but I want to be seen as a trustworthy
person, that's not just about the purchaser, that's in society. So I
want people to see that I stand by my word even if
it means a little cleaning things up afterwards. Okay. So גבי בני
נמי nami ניחא ליה דליקו בהימנותיה *Gabei Bnei Nami Nichei Lei De-Leku
Be-Heimanutei*. That's not not wanting a negative, that's wanting a positive. So
since I want the positive, even by the kids I want them
to see that I'm a trustworthy person. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says no, סוף סוף קרו ליה בני לוקח גזלנא *Sof Sof Karu
Lei Bnei Loke'ach Gazlana*. It's not going to be any good. The
kids are also going to call me a גזלן gazlan. *Gazlan*, okay,
so just if I don't want to be called a גזלן gazlan.
*Gazlan* I'm going to want it to be valid even with the
kids themselves. אלא Ela, איכא בינייהו דמית גזלן gazlan *Ela Ika Beineihu
De-Mis Gazlan*. So the גזלן gazlan *Gazlan* is the one who died.
Now of course you can't buy it from אלי *Eli* after he
dies, so תוספות Tosafot *Tosofos* says he basically bought it from אלי
*Eli* on his deathbed. He knew his death was imminent, okay. So
therefore now that might make a difference in terms of his intent.
מאן דאמר ניחא ליה לאיניש דלא ליקריוה גזלנא *Man De-Amar Nichei Lei
Le-Inish Delo Likreye Gazlana*, I don't... the person doesn't want to get
called a גזלן gazlan, *Gazlan*. המית *Ha-Mis*, after he's dead, what does
he care? He's not going to... I understand, we'll see it. But
if you want a reputation of being like a trustworthy person, or
you want your words to be established, הכא נמי אף על גב
דמית ניחא ליה דליוקמו בהימנותיה. nicha lei deliukmu biheimanutei. So here it's
also, I guess, you want that the act—I don't know what the
logic is of the difference, the assumption that I don't care what
people call me after I'm dead, but if I positively want a
positive reputation, not just I'm afraid of a negative, I actually want
a positive, that's something that maybe is something I'm going to want
to ensure, you know, even after I die. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says—but the גמרא Gemara of course says no real difference. The
גמרא Gemara says like this: למאן דאמר הכא נמי אף על גב
דמית ניחא ליה דליוקמו בהימנותיה. Leman de'amar hacha nami af al gav
demit nicha lei deliukmu biheimanutei. סוף סוף קרו ליה בני בני גזלנא.
Sof sof karu lei benei benei gazlana. No, even if it's just
not wanting to be called a גזלן, gazlan. you know, you don't
want your kids to be called the sons of a גזלן, gazlan
and that by calling your kids the sons of a גזלן, gazlan,
they're still calling you a גזלן. gazlan. אלא, fine, so none of
those are differences. איכא בינייהו דיהבי במתנה. Ika beinaihu deyavei bamatana. I
gave it to Michael as a gift. So, no, you didn't pay
me. Forget the paying. I gave you a gift. Michael, I just
got this new plot of land, it just fell onto—into my, you
know, I just—I just chanced by it after stealing it from Eli.
Here, I'm going to give it to you as a gift because
I like you so much. Okay? He said the sons of the
Rabba, I think he says the sons of the person. No, that
was earlier. Now we're at the sons of the robber. Okay, איכא
בינייהו דיהבי במתנה. Ika beinaihu deyavei bamatana. I gave it to Michael
as a gift, this field I stole. למאן דאמר ניחא ליה דליוקמו
בהימנותיה, Leman de'amar nicha lei deliukmu biheimanutei, I want to be seen
as a trustworthy person, so מתנה matana נמי ניחא ליה דליוקמו בהימנותיה.
So also by a gift, you know, I don't want to be
seen as somebody who objects to give a gift and then the
gift gets taken away from the person. If I said I was
giving you a gift, I'm going to try to establish it as
a gift. למאן דאמר ניחא ליה דלא ליקרי גזלן, Leman de'amar nicha
lei dela likrei gazlan, you don't want to be called a גזלן.
gazlan, אמרי מאי גזילנא מינך? Amrei mai gazilna minach? What did I
steal from you? I gave—you know, you didn't lose any money. I
gave it to you as a gift, then I bought it from
Eli, now I'm taking it back. Okay, so you could say I'm
not a good guy, I don't keep my promises, I told you
I was giving you this gift, but you're not going to call
me a גזלן. gazlan You know, what did I steal from you?
Yes. He stole from you. That might be true, but Michael isn't—but
Eli I paid. So the question is, right? So whatever I'm doing
by paying Eli, that's to get rid of being called a גזלן
gazlan or whatever. Now the question is what implication does it have
in terms of the relationship with Michael? Now the funny thing about
all of this is, is that if you go ahead and you
say, okay, so let's say I get up and I announce I
am buying this from Eli and I don't care if Michael calls
me a גזלן gazlan? and I don't care what whatever, I'm buying
it from Eli for the express purpose that I can then take
it back from Michael. Okay? And I am not doing it to
establish my sale to Michael. Will that matter? Like is this really
a question of what's in this guy's דעת da'at or is this
just a question of how we legally are going to define the
transaction? You know, it seems like it's the second. It seems like
we're going to determine that this is like a general behavior or
we're going to either we really believe this is psychologically how people
act or this is socially what we think is best or whatever
it is, and therefore we're going to just define that that's what
that transaction means. Okay, but that's an interesting question since in the
end the גמרא Gemara ultimately roots it in the person's psychology, what
happens if the person is explicit about it? Yeah. How have we
lost the train of possibility where you're buying it from Eli so
that you can take it back from Michael? Well, the פסק psak
that רב Rav, said was, was that I give it to—that I'm
buying it in order that Michael can have it. And now we're
explaining it for these various reasons. But if in the case like
the גמרא Gemara said מתנה, matana, according to one side of it
that it was about not being called a גזלן, gazlan and then
I gave it to Michael as a מתנה, matana, within that possibility,
if I bought it from Eli, I'd be able to take it
back from Michael. Okay, so there is still that possibility in the
scenario of מתנה matana if you think the reasoning is about being
called a גזלן. gazlan, But as the גמרא Gemara is about to
continue, the גמרא Gemara is going to ignore the גזלן gazlan, idea,
being called a גזלן, gazlan and focus on in order to establish
my trustworthiness. And once we say that that's what it's based on,
then it covers all cases. So yes, so then at the end
of the day I'm always giving it to Michael because it's always
going to be interpreted as wanting to establish my trustworthiness even in
the case of מתנה. matana. So then you can't take it back
from him. Correct. We're always going to assume the reason I bought
it from Eli was because I wanted to be, you know, make
myself a trustworthy guy. Okay. Is this construct predicated on the willingness
of that owner, Eli, to sell the property? Michael couldn't say I
want to buy and Eli says I'm not selling. No, no, wait.
Yeah, no, the case is that after I bought it from Eli,
how do we interpret that purchase? Michael didn't buy from Eli. I
bought it from Eli. And how do we interpret that purchase after
I bought it? You're right. If Eli didn't sell it, then it's
a moot case. Correct. All right. Right. Correct. Everybody—but he has to
go to Eli and say I want and Eli says I'm not
selling. I understand. We're dealing with a particular scenario. Okay, now פשיטא,
peshita, now we're going to continue within this case about variations of
when when I read that I bought it from Eli, then we
assume it's in order to validate the sale to Michael. What about
if I got it from Eli in some other way—excuse me, we're
going to do that in a minute. What about other types of
scenarios? Okay, let's say I went ahead and rather than just—I sold
it to Michael and then I figured, you know, make a lot
of money off of the same plot of land, it wasn't mine
to begin with. If I sold it to Michael and then I
sold it to Jenna and then I sold it to everybody, okay?
And then I bought it from Eli. So there's nobody, why shouldn't
Michael get it? Right? I mean I have you guys, I could
tell you I'm gonna be out. So clearly I am not trying
to establish myself as a trustworthy person by Michael just after I
sold it to five people, okay? So זבנה Zavna if I sold
it to somebody else or אורתה, Orsa, now אורתה Orsa means I
was מוריש morish it, which is a little bit funny because I
can't מוריש morish something and then buy it from Eli. So presumably
it means like I put it in my will or something, you
know, I not that I actually died and bequeathed it, I bequeathed
it in my will. Okay, יהבתה במתנה Yahvta B'matana or even if
I just gave it as a gift to someone else and then
I go and buy it from Eli, לאו במקום לקוח קבעי, Lav
Bimkom Lokeach Kavai, then when I buy from Eli it is not
in order to allow Michael to have it because after I sold
it to Michael I did other things with it as well, so
clearly I'm just a גזלן. gazlan Which means what, meaning that I
keep that land and now I can take it away from you
and all those other people that I just well if it's still
in my will I would have to change my will, but anyway,
but basically I get to take it back. Okay, we don't assume
that my buying from Eli is to give any of you rights
to that land. Then how do I get my money back from
you? That might be according to רב. Rav Okay, now נפלה ליה
בירושה. Nafla Lay Be-yerusha. Now let's say the person I stole the
plot of land from was actually a relative of mine, okay, and
then that person died and then I inherited it. So I sold
it to Michael and then I inherited that plot of land. Okay,
so therefore it just happened by itself. So should we say in
that case I'm trying to establish my sale to Michael? No, there's
nothing to indicate that I'm trying to make that a valid sale
anymore. So in that case ירושה ממילא היא, Yerusha mimmila hee, that
happened automatically by itself. ולאו איהו קטרח אבתרה. Velau ihu katarach avasrah.
I'm not trying—you know, there's a logic—after I sold it to Michael
I'm going and looking and trying to buy the plot of land,
that would be interpreted as a way of making legitimate the sale
I did to Michael. If by chance I happen to inherit the
land, we're not going to interpret it that way. Okay? And then
I keep it and I'm allowed to take it back from you.
Yep. Okay, so ולאו איהו קטרח אבתרה. Velau ihu katarach avasrah. Okay,
now of course you could say maybe I was hard up for
money, you know, there's all these cases especially in these like 19th-century
novels, right, about people, you know, these like, you know, whatever, anyway,
they like they're like waiting for a ירושה, Yerusha, they're totally poor
but they're from nobility or whatever it is, you know, from the
upper class. So I'm hard up for money but I know that
I'm going to be coming into my inheritance sometime soon, so I
sell the plot of land before I inherit it, you know, so
maybe there I actually do want that person to have it, I
just needed the money earlier, you know, but we'll see about a
possibility of that coming up. But at this stage we're saying there's
no evidence that I'm trying to make that sale good, it was
just by chance I inherited it, you know, that's seen as happening
automatically, so therefore I'm able to take the field back. Okay, so
in that case where were we? גביה איהו בחובו. Gavya ihu bechovo.
Now let's say Eli there who I stole the plot of land
from actually owes me money. Maybe that's why I stole the plot
of land, he wasn't paying me up or I don't know what.
Okay, so I stole the plot of land, I sold it to
Michael, but actually Eli owes me $10,000. So now I go to
בית דין Beis Din and I have to collect my $10,000 from
Eli, I say, you know what, I'll just take the plot of
land that I've been squatting on, we'll have that as payment for
my debt. So will that then mean validate the sale to Michael?
Because maybe the reason is it seen like I'm just doing that
to get paid or is it seen like no, maybe the reason
I'm taking that plot of land for payment for my debt is
in order to make the sale I made to Michael legitimate. If
you really wanted to go—if you really wanted to go after it
for the debt, you would have gone to בית דין, Beis Din,
no? Well maybe I did go through בית דין. Beis Din. So
חזינא. Chazina. From the very beginning? No, we're not talking about the
beginning. Once I actually come to take the—to collect my debt, am
I doing it because I want my money, סתם, Stam, or am
I doing it specifically with this plot of land in order to—because
I also want to legitimate the sale I made to you. So
חזינא, Chazina, we look at it. אי אית ליה ארעא אחריתי, Ei
is lei ara achriti, if Eli had other plots of land ואמר
האי בעינא, V'amar hai be'ina, I want hai—you know, I want this
one, I want the one that I sold to Michael, so then
we say לאוקמי קמי לוקח קבעי. Le'ukme kamei lokeach kavai. So the
reason I was מקפיד Makpid to get to—you know, to collect my
debt specifically with this plot of land was in order to legitimate
the sale I made with Michael. That's why I wanted to make
sure it was this plot of land because I'd already sold it
to Michael and I wanted to make that a legitimate sale. Eli
has other land? Or is it the you of other land? Eli
has other land. I could have taken other plots, and the reason
I took this plot was because it was the plot I sold
you and I wanted to make that a legitimate sale. ואי לא,
V'ei lo, and if you don't have any other plots, Eli didn't
have any other plots of land, so then we don't say the
reason I took it was to legitimate the sale, the reason I
took it was to get my debt paid. So ואי לא זוזי
הוא דבעי איפרועי. V'ei lo zuzei hu de-vaei ipruei. Okay, I'm only
doing it because I want to be have my debt paid off.
Okay, is that clear? So basically the common rule here is if
I am clearly going out of my way to purchase this plot
of land, we say it is in order to make good that
bogus sale that we did a few—that I did a few months
ago. But if it just happens by chance that I get the
land, or I'm doing it for other reasons to get a debt
paid off, and it wasn't—and I wasn't choosing this plot over other
plots, it was just the only plot that was available, then we
say it is not done for the purpose of making legitimate the
earlier sale. And then I can take it back, right. Okay, good,
yeah. So he's deciding how he wants his debt paid? Correct. I
mean the owner may say that I'm going to pay you in
jewelry. Well, that's true too. So if—if I say I'll take anything
and Eli chooses to give me this plot, we would also say
that would be like ירושה, yerusha, we would also say that that's
not seen as something that validates the sale. You had a question,
Jetta? Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Now, okay,
okay, יהבו ליה במתנה. yahavu lei bematana. Now, let's say Eli gifts
me the plot of land after I sold it from him. Okay,
I stole it from him and then he decided to give it
to me as a gift. He knew I was hard up for
cash otherwise I wouldn't do such a terrible thing. He stole it
from me. Well, I stole it from Mike, I stole it from
Eli, I sold it to Mike, and then Eli gave it to
me as a gift. He says, "טוב, tov, I know you're a
good guy, you obviously must have needed the money." It's like the
חפץ חיים Chofetz Chaim story. You know the חפץ חיים Chofetz Chaim
story? He brings—he has somebody stay in his house and then, you
know, turns out the guy basically like steals his silverware and is
like running out of the house and the חפץ חיים Chofetz Chaim
is running after him saying, "אני מוחל אני מוחל!" Ani mochel, ani
mochel! So Eli says to me, "I know you must have really
needed the money, so just keep the plot of land." Okay, now
does me now that I got that plot of land—I didn't—it doesn't
seem like I made any effort to get it, right, after I
sold it to Mike? So now that I own it, does that
validate the sale to Mike or not? So let's take a look.
יהבו ליה במתנה. yahavu lei bematana. So פליגי בה רב אחא ורבינא.
pligi bah Rav Acha veRavina. רב אחא Rav Acha and רבינא Ravina
debated. חד אמר מתנה כירושה. chad amar matana k'yerusha. It's like I
inherited it. It was all just chance and therefore I didn't do
any effort in order to get it. So it's not seen like
my getting that land is an attempt of my—on my part to
validate the sale to Mike. וממילא umimeila it happened by itself. What?
So he paid—he purchased? Well, yeah, we פוסקין pasken like רב Rav
against שמואל so I would reimburse Mike. וחד אמר מתנה כמכר. ve'chad
amar matana k'mecher. No, it's like a sale. How is getting a
gift like a sale? It's like I exerted effort. There was like
a transactional nature to it. דאי לאו דטרח וארצי קמיה, de'ilav detarach
ve'artzi kamei, had I not gone to effort and tried to like,
you know, appease, you know, Eli there and like make it, you
know, make it attractive to him, you know, sort of sell it
to him, the idea that he should give me a gift, לא
יהבו ליה מתנה. lo yahavu lei matana. Okay, he wouldn't have given
me a gift. He only gives me a gift because, you know,
because I tried to encourage him to give me a gift. להכי
טרח וארצי קמיה, lehachi tarach ve'artzi kamei, so that's why I went
to that effort, in order to find favor in Eli's eyes and
to encourage him to give me this gift, כי היכי דליקום בהימנותיה,
ki heichi deleikum beheimunutei, so the same way that I went to
effort to buy it so to legitimate my sale to Mike, why
did I go to all this effort to, you know, be so
nice to Eli there and appease him and butter him up and
all that so he would give me the gift of the land?
Because ultimately I'm trying to legitimate my sale to Mike. Okay, so
we look at that as a type of a מכר. mecher We
see that it doesn't come by chance, it comes through effort and
there's some transactional nature to it. It's a fascinating question in general
in הלכה halacha whether מתנה matana is considered like מכר or not.
Do you basically have an attitude like, you know, you could say
it's a cynical attitude, but you know, not necessarily. You could also
say like it's about general reciprocity, you know? People give gifts, you
know, normally because you did, you know, even if—even if they don't
have a cynical attitude, but why do they feel warm towards you
to give you a gift? It's usually because of some good, you
know, something good that you've done to them and because of—so there's
usually some reciprocity going on. So therefore it raises a general question
whether to look at gifts as sales in areas where that distinction
matters. Okay, but here the גמרא Gemara says that maybe particularly the
timing of it, after I sold it to Mike, you gave me
a gift, we're going to assume that that came through some effort
on my part. Okay, and because we're going to assume it came
through some effort on my part, it ultimately is to validate the
sale to Mike. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, ועד אימת ניחא ליה דליקום בהימנותיה? ve'ad eimat nicha lei deleikum
beheimunutei? If we're going to say that I am doing it, my
getting that land is in order to validate the sale to Mike,
how long do we say that's true? Let's say ten years later
I buy—I buy it from Eli. Okay, at that stage I'm still
trying to validate my sale to Mike, right? You know, well, I
don't know, then why didn't I buy it ten years ago? Maybe
he wouldn't sell it. I don't know. Of course. Maybe then because
maybe you had a change of heart, you're like—Oh, maybe I actually
finally got some money together. Right. Oh, that's true. Okay, but you
know, but it's also quite possible that after a long passage of
time, I've, you know, that's all past history. He's angry at me,
he's calling me a גזלן, I don't know what he's going to
whatever, but you know, maybe—so I don't know. It's a good question.
Right, good question. Actually, in for this יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, you
know, period of year, how much back do you sort of still
want to make good on all those mistakes you made many years
ago? So until when are we saying that you're trying to establish
your trustworthiness? So אמר רב הונא עד שעת העמדה בדין. amar Rav
Huna ad she'at ha'amada bedin. Until the point that Eli takes... takes
me to דין. din. So if Eli basically takes me to דין
din for stealing his land, okay, and what? Until basically it's found
out, right? So wait, wait, wait, no, I might have said that
wrong. Let me just check רשי Rashi again. No, well actually he's
going to take Michael to דין din because Michael's now the
one sitting on his land, not okay, wait one minute, let me
just check רשי. Rashi.
Right, so basically now it's finally all become exposed, okay? Eli has
now come to בית דין, beis din, wants his land back, is
bringing Michael to דין din because Michael's the one sitting on the
land. Michael is going to of course, as we פוסקן pasken like
רב, going to now ask, demand the money back from me, okay?
So in that case where it's now like all exposed and it's
coming up to the court case, if I let it wait until
that
point, it's sort of like being מודה בקנס modeh b'knas after the
עדים eidim came forward, right? You know, if now I'm coming to
do it, the only reason I'm coming forward and trying to fix
it or whatever, do something, is not to establish my trustworthiness, but
it's because it's all been exposed.
But the גזלן sitting on a time bomb. He doesn't know when
it's going to explode.
I understand, okay? So but once that happens, then we say if
at that stage I buy it from Eli, okay? Now of course,
it's very funny, you could say the very fact that now it's
coming for דין din and it has been exposed and everybody's now
calling me a גזלן or whatever and I'm buying it from you
is because I actually want to smooth things over. You know, let
me look, I'll buy it from you, Michael can keep it, we
can all go home peacefully, right? So it's interesting, you could see
דווקא davka that that is
what I'm trying to do. But the assumption is that if it
waited that long, then I'm not doing it on my own initiative,
I'm doing it because it all became exposed, I'm not trying to,
you know, fix things, yes.
They'd have to make a fortune. Does it make a difference how
long they've been there? Because you know, if I had three years
of חזקה...
chazakah No, חזקה chazakah is irrelevant here.
So I can't say that oh yeah, it's presumably Eli's מוחל? moichel?
No, no.
I mean, well, no. חזקה chazaka has to have a טענה, ta'anah,
we'll worry about that in בבא בתרא. Bava Basra. No, okay, so
fine, fine, got it. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: עד שעמדו בדין. ad she'amadu badin. כי רב אמר עד דמטי
אדרכתא לידיה. Ki Rav Amar ad d'mati adrach'ta l'yadei.
No, no, no, that's not enough is עמדו בדין, amadu badin, is
Michael got the field back from Eli, Eli got the field back
from Michael, then Michael wants בית דין beis din to get me
to reimburse him because we פוסקן pasken like רב, to reimburse him,
and now בית דין beis din is going to write for Michael
a writ of seizure that allows Michael to come and basically seize
my property, you know, in payment of his debt, okay? So after
we got to that point that he's about to seize my property
in payment of my debt, then we don't, now of course exactly
that point you could say the opposite, that's why I'm now buying
it from Eli in order to make it all go...
Right, but you're doing it because you're forced. So even if that's
your intention, you've been forced into it.
Right, but like it's not a הלכה halacha like of מודה בקנס,
modeh b'knas, like I don't understand why just because I'm forced, why
isn't that... okay fine, I'm doing it because I was forced into
a corner, but what am I trying to do right now? I'm
trying to actually smooth things... maybe the point is that now the
field has clearly been given back to Eli, so there's no field
to now transact to establish with Michael. He's taken his field back,
we're only dealing now with Michael getting his money back. So maybe
that's the point. I don't see why being forced is as much
of an issue, but I do see the fact that once Eli's
taken his field back and we're up to the point of Michael
being reimbursed, there's no sale to Michael to establish anymore.
Well, then it feels more like the נעילה n'neila or whatever that
was, like it's happening to happen to you, that you're you
are...
Right, but but after all those things happen, now I'm going to
the effort to buy it from Eli. I don't know, to me
I don't see the fact that it was forced as much as
like now it's like a past history. You know, that story is
done with, we're on to stage two, you can't fix stage one
anymore. You know, especially once Eli has taken the field back and
we're only up to Michael getting reimbursed. Okay, let's just read the
last one: רב פפא אמר עד דמתחלין יומי אכרזתא. Rav Papa amar
ad d'matchlin yomei achrasta.
No, it's not even immediately after Michael gets the writ of seizure,
but after he gets the writ of seizure, there's a process of
like of auctioning off my property, making a public announcement, okay, you
know, Doe has to sell off his property in order to pay
back Michael, we're going to have an auction on this date or
whatever so that way we can get the best price for the
property that we have a public auction, and only after that period
of making the announcements for the auction begins, then we see that
like okay, now we're really totally in a different stage here.
So they can't just value your land and just take it? What...?
Yeah, I don't know, we'll see that this was the best way
to have a fair valuation, yeah.
Does he have to go to jail or is he sold into
a...?
No, that's the thing, there's no jail. I mean yeah, okay, there's
a case of גניבה gneivah whatever, there's basically no jail. Okay, all
right, so anyway whatever it is, at those stages clearly...?
Could he be sold as a slave if they don't have any
money?
In the case of גנב, ganav, but only under very specific circumstances.
Okay, so anyway so the גמרא Gemara says like this, so anyway,
whatever it is, whether it's because he's being forced or whether because
we're already clearly at stage two, it's no longer in the context
of validating the original
Now, now we're done. We're done with the circumstances under when we
assume my buying it from Eli is in order to legitimate the
sale to Michael. The question we now have is, okay, but I
bought it from Eli six months later. How how did that act,
I only own it in July. How am I, you know, what's
the transaction that's making Michael get it? He did the act of
being קונה koneh in January. So the גמרא Gemara says, so מתיב
ליה רמי בר חמא: מכדי, האי לוקח במאי קני להאי ארעא? masiv
leh Rami bar Chama: Michdi, hai lokeiach be-mai kani le-hai ara? How
did Michael get that שטר shtar in January? בהאי שטר, be-hai shtar,
with the writ that we wrote in January? האי שטר חספא בעלמא
הוא, hai shtar chaspa be-alma hu, that's a piece of junk, it's
a piece of pottery. It was I sold him a field that
I didn't have, so there was no, that was no מעשה קניין,
ma'aseh kinyan, so how's he doing it now? Now תוספות says, of
course, what you could say is like maybe after I bought it
from Eli, Michael does a חזקה chazaka or something, you know, he
keeps on plowing the land which is a חזקה and maybe that
works. But the גמרא says it makes it sound like Michael owns
it automatically after I buy it from Eli. Even if Michael is
over in France somewhere, the field is laying fallow. Okay, the moment
I buy it from Eli, Michael owns it. How does he own
it? Where's the קניין? kinyan? Okay, so אמר ליה רבא: תהא במאמינו.
amar leh Rava: tehei be-ma'amino. Okay, it's a case of like I
trust you. What does that mean I trust you? So when Michael
basically, because remember, this is a case that he knew that the
land was stolen. In fact, it's ironic. If he didn't know that
the land was stolen, Michael, you would say maybe all the more
reason, he bought it in good faith, I'm now buying it from
Eli, maybe I'm really... but no, he knows it's stolen. So since
he knows it's stolen, he says בהוא הנאה דלא קאמר ליה מידי.
be-hu hana'ah dela ka-amar leh midi. Michael says look, Dove, I'm buying
it from you, we all know it's not your land and I'm
not going to demand anything from you, I just trust you. וסמכא
דעתיה, ve-samcha datei, I trust that you'll manage to make the sale
good. Okay, so therefore because that you trusted me to make it
good, even though I sold you and we both knew at that
moment I didn't own it, טרח ומייתי ליה, tarach u-maiti leh, so
and I'm going to the effort to buy it from Eli and
make the sale legitimate. So therefore because you trusted me to do
all of that, גמר ומקני ליה, gamar u-makni leh, so therefore I
had such like, you know, positive feeling for you, Michael, that my
גמר דעת, gmar da'at, my desire for you to own the field
was sufficient. All along by קניינים kinyanim we figure out two things.
I have to have the דעת da'at to transfer it and the
other person has to have the דעת da'at to accept it or
to buy it or whatever. And there has to be a formal
act that shows that it's switching hands. Okay, and sometimes the more
דעת da'at you have, like we dealt in the case before about
a minor and דעת אחרת מקנה, da'at acheret maknah, you know, different
degrees of דעת, da'at, מציאה, metziah, etc., you know, sometimes the less
קניין kinyan you need, the more דעת da'at there is, full דעת
da'at that there is. So every now and then the גמרא comes
up with a possibility that the דעת da'at could be so a
hundred percent without any hesitation that I want you to own it
that you don't even need a מעשה קניין. ma'aseh kinyan. And that
seems to be what it's saying here although again you didn't say
this, is that what we're going to say? Right, it seems like
we're just implicitly since we both knew it was stolen and that's
what the גמרא says ולא קאמר ליה ולא מידי. ve-lo ka-amar leh
ve-lo midi. You know, you didn't even say anything, you just implicitly,
it's so ironic, right, you implicitly trusted me because we all knew
it was stolen. That makes me feel so positive towards you that
if I can buy it, I'm a hundred percent going to want
to do it and you own it. Of course, which basically means
ironically that if you didn't know it was stolen and then I
bought it from Eli, maybe we wouldn't say the same thing, right?
Because even though אדרבה, aderaba, that's the case we should more say
I'm trying to make good by you. Yeah, Jonah, did you want
to say something? I just don't understand, he's trusting you because you're
a גזלן? I mean, it's like a pact or something like you
guys know each other really well and therefore... Yeah, not that we
know each other really well, but like since we all know that
it's stolen and I'm buying it from you, like clearly there's an
implicit understanding that you're going to make good on the sale. I
mean, I wouldn't buy it from you knowing it was stolen unless...
Unless I trusted you that, exactly. Why would I be giving you
money knowing that we all know it's stolen? I wanted to get
a good deal on it. I know, it's very strange, I really
can't explain it. What? It's about doing business with a גזלן and
ולא קאמר ליה ולא מידי? ve-lo ka-amar leh ve-lo midi? He must
be honest? Okay. Unless he didn't view him truly as a גזלן,
but rather someone who dealt in futures and... Yeah, you know, so
that's a good point and I've been wondering about that all along.
All these cases of נמכר שאינה שלו nimchar she-einah shelo although the
גמרא calls it a גזלן, you know, it's like there could always
be like with land in particular. Like if I actually snuck into
Michael's house, right, and I stole his iPhone, we'll do the iPhone
again, okay, and then I sold it to somebody and then afterwards
I bought it from Michael, would we say the same things or
would you say no, in that case I'm a גזלן and like
of course none of this stuff applies. By land, like it's different,
right, because there could be land could be contested and I could
believe it's mine and it turns out that somebody can prove it's
not theirs, but you know, I got it, you know, from five,
you know, I got it from somebody who got it from somebody
who got it from way, way back, somebody else proves that it
originally was theirs. So it could be in this case that even
though it's היכא דאינה שלו, heicha de-einah shelo, right, I think, you
know, the point is maybe yeah, it's not exactly the same as
גזילה, gezeilah, like maybe. There's some understanding that you've been trying to
purchase it, you're in the process of trying to purchase it, and
there's technically at this point it's still not yours, but you're working
at making it yours. So didn't we talk about that explicitly, right?
Didn't we talk about that explicitly a few בלאט *blatt* ago? So
why would it be when we say that that's what it was,
that that's what we're trying to do? Well, no, I mean before
we had the case of נמצא שאינו שלו *nimtza she'eino shelo*, and
this is היכי בר שאינו שלו *heiki bar she'eino shelo*, right? But
it could still be the same. I mean, there's different scenarios, right?
There's one scenario that I walk into Eli's yard with a rifle
and I told Eli, 'get off' and everybody knew that I'm squatting
and sitting on it and then I sold it to Michael. And
there's another scenario which is that I've been trying to buy this
plot of land for many years and there's reason and I have
claims to it or whatever, but we know that technically it's not
mine yet and then I sell it to you, right? Those are
radically different scenarios, in both cases it's היכי בר שאינו שלו *heiki
bar she'eino shelo*, right? So I don't know. All right, let's see
what the גמרא *Gemara* says. Okay. Okay. מתיב רב ששת *Masiv Rav
Sheshes*. Now רב ששת *Rav Sheshes* is going to challenge this idea
that you can sell land before you own it and that eventually
when you get in possession of it, it'll be valid. Okay. Somebody
says to somebody, מה שאירש מאבא מכור לך *ma she'irash mei-aba makhar
lakh*, what I will eventually inherit from my father I'm selling to
you. מה שתעלה מצודתי מכור לך *ma she-ta'aleh metzudasi makhar lakh*, what
I will capture with my net, I'm selling you futures. Okay. This
is the classic גמרא *Gemara* about selling futures. All the fish I
capture in my net this month is sold to you. לא lo,
אמר כלום *lo amar klum*. Oh, I'm sorry, I skipped the line.
לא אמר כלום *lo amar klum*. He didn't say anything. מה שאירש
מאבא היום מכור לך *ma she'irash mei-aba hayom makhar lakh*, what I'll
inherit today, my father is on his... if the guy is saying,
'yeah, he didn't have it yet, but apparently the father's on his
deathbed'. Okay. Or מה שתעלה מצודתי היום *ma she-ta'aleh metzudasi hayom*, what
I capture today with my net, in that case מכור לך דבריו
קיימין *makhar lakh devarav kayamin*, that works.
We'll see why in the גמרא *Gemara*, but let's first focus on
the first part.
Anyway, so but the fish, what was the case then that you're
saying? I sold you fish even before I... both cases you sold
me fish before you got them. Yeah, I know. One was just
what I'll capture today as opposed to what I'll capture this month.
Okay, anything more than a day. Exactly. Exactly. Okay, we'll see about
the second case in the גמרא *Gemara*, but anyway, you see clearly
I can't sell something before I own it, even if, and the
case of fish is a case where I go to the effort
to get the fish, it's not like the case of inheriting, and
even so it doesn't validate the earlier sale even though I go
to the effort to get it. All of this is essentially a
case of a future. Okay. And like the point made before, there's
no גנב *ganev* or גזילה *gezeilah* going on here, it's selling something
that you're actually trying to get and you will get and in
the case of fish actually will get through your efforts, and nevertheless
it doesn't make it a valid sale. So it's a very good
question. So אמר רמי בר חמא האי גברא ואיתיופתא *amar Rami bar
Chama hai gavra ve-at-yufta*. So רמי בר חמא *Rami bar Chama* said
about רב ששת *Rav Sheshes*, 'oh, that's a תלמיד חכם *talmid chacham*,
that's a שאלה *shayla*, that's a good question'. אמר רבא Amar Rava,
גברא קחזינא תיופתא לא קחזינא *amar Rava gavra kachazeina tiyufta lo kachazeina*.
I see a תלמיד חכם *talmid chacham*, I don't see any question.
Why was that not a question? Seems like a pretty good question.
So he says, הכא סמכא דעתיה והכא לא סמכא דעתיה *hacha samcha
daiteih ve-hacha lo samcha daiteih*. So in one case he relies on
you and in the other case he doesn't rely on you. What's
the difference? הכא סמכא דעתיה דאזיל טרחו ומייתי ליה כי היכי דלא
ליקרי גזלנא *hacha samcha daiteih de-azil tarchu u-maiti lei kichei d-lo nikrei
gazlana*, ah, because by exactly the opposite of what we would have
said. The case that you're more of a גזלן *gazlan* is the
case where it's more legitimate. When I'm selling you land I don't
own because somebody else owns it, not because I haven't captured the
fish yet, because somebody else owns it, then if I don't make
that sale legitimate, I'm going to get called a גזלן *gazlan*. And
therefore I'm going to go to the extra effort and therefore we
all are sincere about it and it's a binding transaction when I'm
eventually able to buy the field retroactively somehow or at that time
because of a גמר דעת *g'mar da'as*. הכא לא סמכא דעתיה *hacha
lo samcha daiteih*. But buying fish as a future, I'll say, 'I
don't know if he's going to capture the fish he says he's
going to, I don't know how successful he's going to be'. And
he doesn't have any big incentive to make it legitimate. If it's
not legitimate and he doesn't capture fish, I'll get my money back.
So therefore you don't really believe it's going to happen. Okay. So
again, ironically, the more the guy is a גזלן *gazlan*, the more
we're all really committed to the sale. Okay. שלחו לקמיה דרבי אבא
*shalchu lekamei de-Rabbi Abba*. They sent this question to רבי אבא בר
זבדא *Rabbi Abba bar Zavda*. אמר להו זו אינה צריכה לפנים Zu
einah tzricha lifnim, *amar lehu zu eina tzricha lifnim*. Now there's a
big... there's two לשון *lashon* in רש"י *Rashi* what זו אינה צריכה
לפנים *zu eina tzricha lifnim* means. One is that this is such
a good question that it's not even worth asking the people in
the ישיבה *yeshiva*, they won't even be able to give an answer
to it, it's such an absolute question, meaning the question of the
fish against the idea of the field. The other way, the way
it's normally used in rabbinic literature, and רש"י *Rashi* also says, is
that you don't even have to look at this, this is such
an obvious answer. Okay. The answer's so obvious. What a silly question,
this issue about the fish, so clearly there's a difference there. אמר
רבא Amar Rava, זו צריכה לפנים ולפני ולפנים tzricha lifnim velifnei velifnim,
*amar Rava zu tzricha lifnim velifnei velifnim*. Okay. Like יום כיפור *Yom
Kippur*, very appropriate for יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*. This really needs investigation.
Okay. One doesn't need to be looked at. No, no, we really
do need to investigate it, but there's an answer. What's the answer?
הכא סמכא דעתיה והכא לא סמכא דעתיה *hacha samcha daiteih ve-hacha lo
samcha daiteih*. In the case by the case of the field, since
otherwise you'd be a גזלן *gazlan*, everybody would... Nearly intends, going to
work to make it go through, and there’s גמירות דעת, gemirut דעת.
and in the case of the fish, there’s not גמירות דעת. gemirut
da'at Okay. הוה עובדא בפומבדיתא, Havah uvda bepumbedita, I mean right? Because
now that take a look, yeah. Well, we're going to see it
in a minute. הוה עובדא בפומבדיתא, Havah uvda bepumbedita, there was a
story case in Pumbedita and ואספי Ve'asfei and they challenged it from
the case by the fish. There was a case by the field
where they said it was legitimate after he bought the field and
they said well what about this case of the fish? ואמר ליה
רב יוסף, Ve'amar leih Rav Yosef, זו אינה צריכה לפנים, you don't
even have to look at this case. ואמר ליה אביי, Ve'amar leih
Abaye, no, צריכה לפנים ולפני ולפנים, you really have to investigate it,
but here's the answer. הכא סמכא דעתיה הכא לא סמכא דעתיה. Hacha
samcha da'ateih hacha lo samcha da'ateih. Okay. Now we're going to look
at the important difference between selling the what I will get today
with my net or what the guy's what he's going to inherit
today from his father as opposed to in some distant in some
future. מאי שנא רישא ומאי שנא סיפא, Mai shna reisha umai shna
seifa, what's the difference? אמר רב יוחנן, Amar Rav Yochanan, סיפא, Seifa,
מה שיאורש מאבא היום, mah sheiyorash me'abba hayom, משום כבוד אביו. mishum
kvod aviv. So why is he desperate to sell property that on
the day his father is about to die later today? So we
assume it's because he needs money for funeral expenses. Okay, and therefore
it's almost like a תקנה takkanah that we're going to let that
sale go through because it's such an urgent need. Okay. ומה שתעלה
מצודתי היום, Umah sheta'aleh metzudati hayom, how about the case about the
fish? משום כדי חיי mishum k'dei chayei because why is somebody selling
it? Because they're basically, they you know they need to, you know,
it's not like you're selling some futures and it's a bigger business,
you know, like a sort of like a more large-scale business transaction.
You know, I mean you just need food to put you know
money to put food on the table today. You know, one day's
catch is not a lot of money. So if you're so desperate,
why are you so desperate? Wait till later in the day after
you've caught the fish. Why are you so desperate to sell it
today before you've caught the fish? Clearly there's some urgency. So this
way... anyway, the way רש״י Rashi understands this, now you you know
is that it doesn't actually address the גמירות דעת gemirut da'at, issue.
It addresses you're in a dire situation and somehow we're going to
let it go, we're going to like some type of a תקנה
takkanah that we'll let it be valid. Okay, but now we deal
with the case about futures. Okay, let's take a look. אמר רב
הונא אמר רב, Amar Rav Huna amar Rav, האומר לחבירו שדה שאני
לוקח וכשאקחנה קנויה לך מעכשיו. Ha'omer lachavero sadeh she'ani loke'ach uchesh'ekkachennah knuyah
lach me'achshav. This field that I'm hoping to purchase, once I wind
up purchasing it, you should own it as of now. So that's
essentially selling a future. קנה, Kanah, it works! Okay now that's very
strange because before we've been saying that it doesn't work, only in
very limited situations that we say it's a גמירות דעת, you know,
because otherwise he'll be called a גזלן and all those cases. Generally
this doesn't work selling a future, right? It's דבר שלא בא לעולם.
davar shelo ba le'olam. So אמר רבא, so says Rava, מסתברא מילתא
דרב בשדה סתם. mistabra milta deRav besadeh stam. That makes sense if
you say I'm going to sell you a field, not a particular
one. Why? Because there's lots of fields on the market. So then
you can sell a future. Okay. אבל בשדה זו, Aval besadeh zu,
this field, לא, that wouldn't be legitimate, work. מי יימר דמזבין ליה
ניהליה? Mi yeimar demazbin leih nihaleih? How do I know I'll be
able to purchase this field? Okay, but this is very important because
he says conceptually if stuff is readily available to be purchased, even
though and then you can sell a future, right? Well, fish, although
it's an interesting question, do you know that you'll catch the fish?
But it's more relevant for the case of futures, right? I know
for sure I'll be able to buy the stuff on the stock
market. There is always going to be that stuff available. רמב״ם Rambam
פוסקs pasken that we do not say you cannot sell a דבר
שלא בא לעולם, davar shelo ba le'olam, I mean let me reframe
that. You can sell a דבר שלא בא לעולם davar shelo ba
le'olam or something that you don't own if it is readily available
like in the stores. So I can go ahead and sell you
a a gallon of milk, okay, before I own it and then
I'm going to go and buy it because it's not considered out
of my control, it's not considered even though technically I don't own
it, but since it's easily accessible and there's nothing that's going to
prevent me from getting it, then actually now maybe it'll only go
through once I buy it, it doesn't go through as of now,
I don't have it yet. Okay, so that's the distinction being made
here between שדה זו sadeh zu and שדה סתם. sadeh stam. And
that might actually hold להלכה. lehalacha. Yeah, yeah, probably, right. Okay. And
then right, so אמר רבא, now so that's the distinction that Rava
is making. But now the גמרא just says that's not what רב
meant. רב was going even further. והאלהים, Veha'elohim, in true, is that
really true? No, in truth, אמר רב אפילו בשדה זו. amar Rav
afilu besadeh zu. Rav really is willing to פוסק pasken that you
can sell something you don't own even a specific thing that you
might not be able to buy. Why? Because he פוסקs like רבי
מאיר. Rabbi Meir. מכדי רב כמאן אמרה לשמעתיה? Michdi Rav keman amrah
lishmatih? Who is Rav going like? To רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Like
Rabbi Meir. דאמר אדם מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם. De'amar adam makneh
davar shelo ba le'olam. And Rabbi Meir says you can sell something
that doesn't yet exist or that you don't yet own. דתניא, Detanya,
we learned in a ברייתא: braita: האומר לאשה התקדשי לי לאחר שאתגייר,
Ha'omer le'ishah hitkadshi li le'achar she'etgayer, לאחר שתתגיירי, le'achar shetitgayeri, לאחר שאשתחרר,
le'achar she'eshtachrer, לאחר שתשתחררי, le'achar shetishtachreri, לאחר שימות בעליך, le'achar sheyamut ba'aleich,
לאחר שיחלוץ ליך יבמיך, le'achar sheyachlotz lach yevameich, לאחר שנתגרשה. le'achar shenitgarshah.
your sister who I happen to be married to dies. Okay, in
all those cases אינה מקודשת *einah mekudeshet*. It doesn't work. רבי מאיר
אומר *Rabbi Meir omer* מקודשת *mekudeshet*. It does work, even though in
most of those cases it was not something you could make happen.
It was in hands of other people. So you were doing something
that you was not yet able to do and the ability was
out of your hand and it works. So בהאי אשה כשדה זו
דמיא *Behai isha k'sadeh zu damya*. The case of the woman is
like this field. You can't get the husband to die, well you
could but it wouldn't be legal. You couldn't get a lot of
those things to happen, okay, and nevertheless it works, okay, because you
can do something שלא בא לעולם *shelo ba l'olam*. באמרי רבי מאיר
מקודשת *B'amrei Rabbi Meir mekudeshet*. So clearly if you פוסק *pasken* דבר
שלא בא לעולם *davar shelo ba l'olam*, it solves all of these
cases. Okay, but the interesting thing is the two, the three exceptions.
Let's just summarize. Number one, you stole the field and everybody knows
it's stolen and in that case when you actually do buy it
from the original owner, there's seen to be there like everybody is
really committed to making it happen, you shouldn't be called a גזלן
*gazlan* or whatever, there's a גמירות דעת *gmirot da'at*. So that's one
type of a case that it works even though at the time
it didn't work, we'll make it work when you actually buy it.
Okay, other cases normally though what I inherit, what my fish catch,
etc. won't work. But in the case of when you say today,
there might be special situations of urgency that we let it work,
okay, even though you don't yet own it. And the third case,
which is not clear in the גמרא *Gemara*, but it's a distinction
that's raised that רמב"ם *Rambam* actually פוסק'ס *paskens* like which is extremely
relevant for the futures market is stuff that is readily and easily
available and I can just, you know, in the general market. So
that type of a thing, even though I don't own it yet,
you might be able to sell it and that's really the whole
question of the futures market. Okay, so nice series of things about
buying and selling things you don't yet own and we'll pick up
with this tomorrow.